<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Ode on St. Cecila's Day perform'd on the 23rd of November, 1696 / set to music by Mr. Nicola Matteis.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53199</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31046</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11769102</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11769102</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48813</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53199)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48813)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1490:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Ode on St. Cecila's Day perform'd on the 23rd of November, 1696 / set to music by Mr. Nicola Matteis.</title>
                  <author>Matteis, Nicola, fl. 1672-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Imprint information suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Without music.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Chetham's Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="song">
            <pb facs="tcp:48813:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->
            <head>An ODE ON St. Cecilias Day. Perform'd on the 23d of <hi>November,</hi> 1696.</head>
            <byline>Set to Muſic by Mr. <hi>Nicola Matteis.</hi>
            </byline>
            <lg>
               <l>ASſiſt, aſſiſt! You mighty Sons of Art,</l>
               <l>In pleaſing Notes your wondrous Skill impart;</l>
               <l>Let Muſick in its gayeſt dreſs appear,</l>
               <l>To crown this day the Queen of all the Year:</l>
               <l>And may the celebrated Day,</l>
               <l>Thoſe Honours which it takes repay,</l>
               <l>Thus let them grace each others Name,</l>
               <l>And gratefully beſtow a mutual Fame.</l>
               <l>Let ev'ry Voice conſpire to raiſe</l>
               <l>Theirs, and bright <hi>Cecilia</hi>'s Praiſe;</l>
               <l>Let the glad Winds diffuſe around</l>
               <l>The Sympathiſing Sound;</l>
               <l>Whilſt from the Strings the ſpritely Notes ſtart forth,</l>
               <l>And cloath themſelves in Air from whence they firſt took Birth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And thou, bleſt Saint, from Heav'n our Breaſt inſpire,</l>
               <l>(Where thou reign'ſt Miſtreſs of the Quire)</l>
               <l>Where you your ſacred Art improve</l>
               <l>To ſing your Maker's Pow'r and Love.</l>
               <l>With eager Joy indulge his Praiſe;</l>
               <l>In various Sounds his various Wonders trace.</l>
               <l>Some Moments from your Triumphs ſpare,</l>
               <l>A while your joyful Notes forbear,</l>
               <l>A while your pleaſing Task forego,</l>
               <l>To caſt a Look on us thy Sons below.</l>
               <l>Attend, Attend our Harmony,</l>
               <l>And liſten to our Songs, as Angels did to thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What mighty Joys from Muſick flow!</l>
               <l>Muſick the greateſt good we Mortals know,</l>
               <l>By which we taſte of Heav'n below.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:48813:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:48813:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 30 -->
               <l>In vain our Paſſions hotly move,</l>
               <l>It checks their Heat, and melts them into Love.</l>
               <l>In vain, we labour to indulge our Grief,</l>
               <l>The ſpritely Violin affords a kind Relief.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From Muſick s Pow'r the World began,</l>
               <l>It ſtill enſlaves, the World's great Maſter, Man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Why ſhould we then it's vaſt Antiquity diſgrace,</l>
               <l>'Call <hi>Jubal</hi> Author of our Race?</l>
               <l>'A nobler Lineage we ſhould claim:</l>
               <l>'From Heav'n alone the Godlike Off-ſpring came.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Er'e Chaos firſt this beauteous frame diſclos'd,</l>
               <l>'And Nature ſtruggled with the Load,</l>
               <l>'The Particles confus d and heavy lay.</l>
               <l>'Nor thro the gloomy Maſs could force their feeble way.</l>
               <l>'But when the Voice deſcending from above</l>
               <l>'Commanded the dull Lump to move,</l>
               <l>'The Lump, tho almoſt dead,</l>
               <l>'Rear d up its chearful Head;</l>
               <l>'Th' armonious Voice inſpir'd a new born Soul,</l>
               <l>Enliven'd by its Sound the nimble Atoms rowl.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tho the fierce Hero calls to Arms,</l>
               <l>And warlike Heat his reſtleſs Mind alarms,</l>
               <l>The Flutes ſoft Voice will ſoon controul</l>
               <l>The raging Paſſions of his Soul:</l>
               <l>Lull'd to a calm and gentle Peace</l>
               <l>The threatning Storm will ceaſe:</l>
               <l>'The pleaſing Voice inſpires</l>
               <l>'Languiſhing thoughts and kind deſires,</l>
               <l>'Whilſt baffled from his Breaſt the angry God retires.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The trembling Slave, tho pale with Fears,</l>
               <l>When the loud Trumpet's Voice he hears</l>
               <l>Feels a ſtrange Fire his Soul invade,</l>
               <l>Collects his new-born Courage to his Aid.</l>
               <l>The warlike Notes impart</l>
               <l>Strength to his Limbs, and Boldneſs to his Heart.</l>
               <l>'Dauntleſs to fight he goes,</l>
               <l>'Stalks thro the Field, and ſwells to meet his Foes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Grand Chorus.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then let all join: Your Souls and Voices raiſe!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis Harmony alone that Harmony can praiſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>May, like your Joys, your Lays be full and great,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Heav'nly Art with Heav'nly Notes to treat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Till wond'ring Angels jealous grow,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And find another Heav'n below.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
